<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Epsom upon the 9th of September, being the day of thanksgiving appointed by His Majesty for the discovery and disappointment of the Republican Plot, and now made publick to obviate false reports by John Turner ...</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38379</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17352187</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17352187</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106412</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106412)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1105:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Epsom upon the 9th of September, being the day of thanksgiving appointed by His Majesty for the discovery and disappointment of the Republican Plot, and now made publick to obviate false reports by John Turner ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes X, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Rye House Plot, 1683 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106412:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Epſom</hi> upon the <hi>9th</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> Being the <hi>Day of Thankſgiving</hi> Appointed by His MAJESTY for the Diſcovery <hi>and</hi> Diſappointment OF THE REPUBLICAN PLOT, And now made publick to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate falſe Reports.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNER,</hi> late Fellow of Chriſts Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quem recitas meus eſt, O fidentine, libellus, Sed malè dum recitas incipit eſſe tuus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Benè agere &amp; malè pati Regium eſt &amp; Regiorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:106412:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106412:2"/>Eccl. X. 20.</bibl>
               <q>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought. For a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the Voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE are met together this day, not in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle, as the manner of ſome is, to Whine againſt the Government in a melting Tone, and ſanctifie the Breach of Law with <hi>Friday-Faces;</hi> to Worſhip God by Affronting his Vicegerent, and diſobey the King for Conſcience ſake, but in a Loyal and Dutiful Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, by the King's expreſs Appointment and Command, not to ſow the Seeds of Sedition, nor to reap an Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt of Blood, but, as becomes good Chriſtians and good Subjects, to deteſt and abominate both one and t'other.</p>
            <p>And thanks be to God that we are met together this day, for it had like to have fared much otherwiſe with us, it wanted but a little, and God, who for our ſins is wroth with his Inheritance, had utterly forſaken his Tabernacle of <hi>Shilo,</hi> and the Tent which he had pitched among men, the Prieſts and the Young men would have Fallen by the Sword, the Maidens would not have been given in M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>riage, and there would have wanted Widows to make Lamentation.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106412:3"/>
            <p>This Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Joy of the whole earth, where God reſides in a peculiar manner, as once between the Cherubims within the Vail of the Temple; this Church of <hi>England</hi> ſo Excellently placed between the two Extremes, of Popery on the one hand, and Fanaticiſm on the other; ſo Pure, ſo Wholſom, ſo Primitive in its Doctrines and in its Diſcipline, ſo juſt and wiſe; this Church that ſtands upon the Rock of Ages, and bids defiance to the Gates of Hell, that is Cemented by the Blood of Confeſſors and Martyrs, and was ſo lately purg'd by the Fire of Tribulation, to make it more beautiful and more ſtrong together, yet for the Hypocriſie of ſome, and for the open profaneneſs of others in her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſhe was now a ſecond time in danger of being loſt, and the dreadful Voice of <hi>Samuel</hi> once more hover'd in the gloomy Sky; <hi>if ye ſhall ſtill do wickedly, ye ſhall be deſtroyed, both ye and your King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For had the King been ſpared, who, as the People ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> is <hi>worth ten thouſand of us,</hi> there might have been ſtill ſome hope remaining, that this poor Church, though once more weltring in a Sea of Bloud, might have ſurviv'd the Calamity of her Sons. But the King and the Monarchy were to fall together, the King and the Duke were both of them to die, the King and his Family were to be extinguiſh'd, and it might have been ſaid of the two Royal Brothers, as once of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan</hi> his Son, <hi>The</hi> King and the Duke <hi>were lovely and pleaſant in their lives, and in their deaths they were not divided, they were ſwifter than Eagles, they were Stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than Lyons, how are the mighty Fallen, and the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of war periſhed. Ye Mountains of Brittain, let there be no dew, neither let the rain deſcend upon you, for there the life of</hi> Charles <hi>was vilely caſt away, the life of</hi> Charles, <hi>as though he had not been Anointed with Oyle. O let it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106412:3"/> not be told in</hi> Gath, <hi>nor publiſh'd in the Streets of</hi> Askelon, <hi>leſt the Daughters of the</hi> Philiſtines <hi>rejoyce, leſt the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſed triumph;</hi> leſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> upbraid us that theſe are the Effects of True Proteſtant Religion, the barbarous Attendants of a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Reformation.</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſacre from this time forward be ſilent, and let the Ghoſts of <hi>Ireland</hi> walk no more, for the Saints have out-done the Cruelties of the Wicked, and <hi>Rome</hi> is Merciful in compariſon of <hi>Geneva!</hi> Have the Papiſts found out a <hi>Clement</hi> and a <hi>Ravillac</hi> that thought it a Pious and a Meritorious Work, to <hi>lop the two Sparks</hi> of the Royal Houſe of <hi>Bourbon;</hi> the Third and Fourth <hi>Henry</hi> ſucceeding one another? And have not our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants had their Court of Juſtice, where an hundred <hi>Clements</hi> and <hi>Ravillacs</hi> ſat together to Murther a King under pretext of Law, and would have made us believe they waſh'd their hands of the Guilt, at the ſame time when they waſh'd their hands of the Guilt, at the ſame time when they waſh'd them in his Bloud? And were not the ſame ſort of Proteſtants, whoſe Bible is of the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Geneva,</hi> the men of <hi>Knoxe's</hi> Principles, and the men after <hi>Calvin's</hi> own heart, were not they whetting the Weapons of Deſtruction, to ſerve the <hi>Second Charles</hi> as they had ſerved the <hi>Firſt,</hi> and make him the Inheritor of his Fathers Fate as well as of his Throne? And as the Fathers death, whom the Indictment called <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> King of <hi>England,</hi> was uſhered in by that of a Pious and a Learned Prelate, the then Archbiſhop and Primate of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, ſo here the inhumane Butchery of a <hi>Scotch</hi> Archbiſhop was, as it were, a Prologue to the intended Murther of the Son, whom in deriſion they were uſed to call the <hi>King of Scots;</hi> although in this indeed the Parallel does not hold, that a Civil War preceded the Martyrdom of the Father, but a Maſſacre more Bloody
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106412:4"/> was to follow that of the Son. For the King was not to fall ſingly by himſelf, but more like a Tartar than a Chriſtian Prince, all his Faithful Servants and Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants were to be made a Sacrifice at his Tomb.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>The Godly Treaſon was not ſatisfy'd</l>
               <l>To kill the King, and quench its thirſty Pride,</l>
               <l>By ſucking at the Royal Orifice,</l>
               <l>This was too mean, too little a Device,</l>
               <l>But as when Wines from Traiterous <hi>Bourdeaux ſent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Are ſtav'd, and flow thorough the gaping vent,</l>
               <l>So the whole Kingdom would at once have bled,</l>
               <l>And its whole Strength at one broad Wound have ſhed;</l>
               <l>While Slaughter in her Purple Veſt array'd,</l>
               <l>Her own fierce deeds with a wan look ſurvey'd,</l>
               <l>And fear'd thoſe Terrours which her ſelf had made.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe are they that ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, having not the Spirit,</hi> and yet pretending to it almoſt as much as Chriſt and his Apoſtles. Good God! that men that cannot get down a Ceremony, though they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo fain, ſhould be able to ſwallow Treaſon and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on! That they that change colour at the ſight of a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, ſhould make no bones of Garments roll'd in Blood! So that the <hi>Prophet</hi> might have ask'd the ſame Queſtion of every one of theſe Religious Monſters, that quarrel with Motes, and yet diſpenſe with Beams, which he ask'd with his uſual Eloquence upon anotheroccaſion <hi>Who is this that comes from</hi> Edom, <hi>with his Garments dyed from</hi> Bozra? <hi>Wherefore art thou red in thine Apparel, and thy Garments like him that treadeth in the Wine Fat?</hi> When our Saviour talk'd to his Diſciples of <hi>eating his Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinking his Blood,</hi> and that no man could be his Diſciple, that did not eat the one, and drink the other, they underſtanding him in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106412:4"/> literal and firſt ſenſe, ſaid among one another, <hi>This is an hard ſaving, who can hear it?</hi> And the Evangeliſt tells us a very little after, That <hi>from that time many of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples went back, and walked no more with him.</hi> Nay, the twelve themſelves were ſtartled at the thing, and in ſome doubt whether they alſo ſhould forſake him or no, as appears by our Saviours queſtion immediately ſubjoyned; <hi>will ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo go away?</hi> So grievouſly were they Scandalized and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at the very thought of <hi>eating Fleſh, and drinking Bloud.</hi> But the religious <hi>Canibals</hi> of our times, make it a light matter to eat the Fleſh, and pick the Bones of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; they exceed in Barbarity the <hi>Sarmatians</hi> of old, who though they drank the Bloud of Horſes, yet could not down with that of Men, this is a knack peculiar to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Party, and yet their Conſciences are tender all this while; their Conſciences are tender, but their Bowels are hard, their Mercies are cruel, their Fore-heads as impudent and impenetrable as the Adamant it ſelf, and they make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for the ſoftneſs of their Heads, by Necks as ſtiff as the <hi>Obelisk</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> or the <hi>tall Monument</hi> at the <hi>Bridge-Foot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who would ever believe that theſe were the very men that were wont to declaim ſo loudly againſt the Popiſh Murthers, that talkt of nothing but <hi>Piedmont,</hi> and the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> and the <hi>Marian</hi> Days, and the <hi>invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Armada,</hi> and the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> the Perſecutions of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> the Churches of <hi>France,</hi> that have been lately ſo perfidiouſly demoliſhed, and the Miniſters of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> that were condemned to the <hi>Gallies,</hi> and uſed to quiet their Children when they cryed, with the Names of <hi>Stephen Gardiner,</hi> and <hi>Bloody Bouner?</hi> but it is nevertheleſs true for being ſtrange; the Papiſt and Fanatick, the Diſſenter and the Jeſuit, as bitter Enemies as they are to one another, yet they tend to a Point, and move about a Centre, they are like <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106412:5"/> and <hi>Levi</hi> Brethren in Iniquity, <hi>Inſtruments of Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are in their Habitations, Curſed be their anger for it is fierce, and their wrath for it is cruel: O my Soul come not thou into their ſecret, unto their Aſſembly be not thou united.</hi> This Age ſtands amazed at ſo horrid a Diſcovery, and the next would ſcarce believe that ſo much Wickedneſs was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in this; were it not that the Conſpirators them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have all of them ſo unanimouſly confeſſed their Guilt; not the Witneſſes only, whom a ſuſpicious Malice may pretend to have accuſed others, that they might ſave themſelves; but ſome have confeſſed the Treaſon by their Flight, even before they were known to be accuſed; others have confeſſed it by practiſing thoſe barbarous Cruelties upon their own Perſons, which were deſigned to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed upon ours; others have owned it at the Bar, and at the place of Execution, where men do not uſe to tell lies againſt themſelves; and he that will not believe a Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, when he comes to dye, acknowledging his Guilt, will remain ſtill in a ſtate of Infidelity, though he and all the Accomplices of his Crime ſhould ariſe together to vouch it from the Dead.</p>
            <p>They have Conſpired together in acknowledging the Treaſon, as well as in committing it; and by that acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment they have prevented themſelves, and we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the ſnares of Death: They have ſhown by ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous, ſo ſeaſonable a Confeſſion, juſt almoſt at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nick of time when the diſmal Tragedy was about to be acted, that there is a Providence preſiding over Humane Affairs, that will not ſuffer Diſloyalty to proſper, and ſo much Wickedneſs to go unpuniſhed, that God will defend and proſper his Anointed, the Defender of the Faith, and the Majeſtique Image of his Perſon, and make every Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Subject take up the Song of <hi>David</hi> in his Mouth, <hi>Verily there is a reward for the Righteous, ſurely there is a God that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106412:5"/> judgeth the Earth:</hi> They have verified the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that Treaſon and Murther will never fail to come out, and juſtified the Counſel of <hi>Solomon</hi> in my Text, <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought; for a bird of the air ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath Wings ſhall tell the matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon occaſion of which words, I ſhall do theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I will demonſtrate to you that Reſiſtance againſt the King, or the Supreme Power, is in all Caſes unlawful; <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall apply that general Theory to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Circumſtances of this Conſpiracy, which was an horrid Complication of the moſt barbarous Cruelty, the moſt perfidious Treachery, and the moſt vile Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude together.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall reflect upon the Fatal Conſequences that would have happened, if the intended Wickedneſs had taken effect.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I ſhall obſerve that there is a ſecret Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence running through all things, and watching over all the Affairs of humane Life, that will not ſuffer ſuch execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Villany to eſcape either undetected or unpuniſhed, <hi>For a bird of the air ſhall carry the voice, and that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, and Laſtly, You ſhall give me leave to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you, as my Duty is, and as yours requires of you upon this Solemn occaſion, that you would lift up your Hearts with Joy and Thankfulneſs to God, who hath done ſo great things for us, and hath wrought ſo great Deliverance for the King and his People, to whoſe eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Providence and Watchful Goodneſs we can only aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe it, that we are not at this day in the ſame Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with ſome of the Conſpirators themſelves, who have deſervedly ſuffered for their Crime, that we have not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106412:6"/> been given over as a prey to our Enemies, as for our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Iniquities and crying Sins we have very well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be; that the Sword hath not been drunk with the blood of the ſlain, and ſurfeited with the fat of the Mighty; and that the ſame voice is not heard howling and ſhrieking in our Streets, that was of old heard in <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah of Galilee; The voice of lamentation, and weeping, and great mourning: Rachel weeping for her children, and would not be comforted, becauſe they are not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all theſe in their order. And Firſt, I ſay, That Reſiſtance againſt the King, or the Supream Power, is in all Caſes unlawful: <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought:</hi> Now the reaſon why Reſiſtance is in all Caſes, and in all its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and Circumſtances abſolutely unlawful, is in ſhort this, That it ſuppoſes an Appeal of the People from the King to themſelves, and makes them Judges of their own Cauſe, which if it be allowed in one Inſtance, there is no avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, but it muſt be granted in all, and by that means the Government is not only very dangerouſly aſſaulted, but utterly overthrown, and the People will obey no longer, nor no further than they pleaſe themſelves, which, what Confuſion and Diſorder it would immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately bring upon the Affairs of Mankind, how giddy, how uncertain, how tumultuous, how dangerous and troubleſome they would be to one another, you may more eaſily conceive within your ſelves, than I can find words to expreſs; the Conſequence of it would be nothing but Anarchy and Riots, and Eternal daſhing of one Man, or one Parties Humour or Intereſt againſt another.</p>
            <p>For to place the Soveraignty, or the laſt Appeal in all the People together is perfect Non-ſenſe, for this Reaſon, becauſe all the People will never be of a Mind ſo long as the World indures, and if they were, there would be no need of Magiſtrates, or of Government: To place it in a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106412:6"/> of the whole Body, though it be no leſs than Treaſon in the Eye of the Law, yet I will be ſo Civil as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be Guilty of Miſpriſion my ſelf, than to turn In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former at this time, only I will obſerve, that ſuch a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition as this does effectually grant all that I contend for, that there is ſomewhere an abſolute and unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Power, which can in no caſe be reſiſted or oppoſed; for if it may, then 'tis no longer the Soveraign Power. But ſince it hath been proved already, that the Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cannot be in the whole Body or Collection of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple taken together, if it be not in a Majority neither, then either it is in the Minor part of the People, ſo as if a Nation were to come to a Poll, the Minor part ſhall have a right of preſcribing to the Major, and the fewer Voices ſhall carry it, which is contrary to the Reaſon of things, and to the Practice of all Ages in popular Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Debates; and beſides, if it be granted, yet it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes a Supream and Soveraign Power, which cannot law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be reſiſted or oppoſed: Or elſe, Laſtly, If the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty be neither in all the People, nor in the Major, nor in the Minor part, nor in the Prince, or the Eſtabliſh'd Government, which the Doctrine of Reſiſtance ſuppoſeth it is not, then either it is no where at all, that is, there is no ſuch thing to be met with as a Supream and unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power, or every private Man is a Prince by himſelf, accountable to none but God, as Soveraign Princes are, and his Dominions extend as far as his Perſon or his ſingle Power or Policy can reach; ſo that at this rate all Society would be immediately diſſolved: And what a bleſſed po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Affairs this would infallibly and unavoidably pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, I take no delight in recounting with my ſelf, but leave it to you to determine at your leiſure, if any of you have leiſure enough to conſider all the Calamities and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs that would follow.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106412:7"/>
            <p>God Almighty expects nothing from us for his own ſake, but only for ours; and therefore all the Duties, as well of Revealed as Natural Religion, are ſo ordered, that they are exactly Calculated and Proportioned to the Peace and Wellfare of Mankind; he commands us to be Chaſt and Temperate in our Lives, juſt in our Dealings, affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and gentle in our Converſations, Merciful to ſuch as are in want, patient in Adverſity, humble and equal in our proſperous Condition, ready to forgive our Enemies, and to be heartily reconciled to ſuch as have injured or offended us, to be Affectionate and Dutiful to our Parents, kind to our Relations, Faithful to our Friends, Careful of our Families, Obedient to our Superiours; but the true reaſon why he expects all this from us, is not that he reaps any thing of Advantage by it, who is entirely bleſſed and happy in himſelf, but only becauſe the practice of theſe Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties is of ſo great and manifeſt importance to the good of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Life, to make us healthful and chearful in our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons, to make us moſt acceptable to others, as well as moſt eaſie to our ſelves, to keep the World in a ſtate of Peace and Friendſhip, and make men live quietly and comfortably together.</p>
            <p>And the ſame is true likewiſe of thoſe Duties which have a more immediate Relation to God himſelf as their Object; he commands us to love and praiſe him, to meditate and fix our thoughts upon him, to pray to him in our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, to truſt in him in our wants, to fly to him as our laſt Refuge in the time of danger, to acknowledge our perpetual obligation to him and our perpetual depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon him, and to humble our ſelves at the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool of his Mercy with Sorrow and Contrition, and with reſolutions of a better Life, at the conſideration of the Sins we have committed aginſt him. The true reaſon of all which is, not that God gets any thing by our Prayers, or that he is any loſer, when we do not humble our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106412:7"/> ſelves before him for our Sins, but becauſe a conſtant ſenſe of the Exiſtence and Being of a God, and of his Preſence in the midſt of us, as a Witneſs and Spectator of all our thoughts and actions; wherever we be, and whatſoever we are doing, or deſigning to do; a ſerious Reflection upon that Power and Juſtice which nothing can reſiſt or bribe, that Knowledge from which nothing can poſſibly be conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that Goodneſs to which we are ſo infinitely obliged, and upon which we have every moment an entire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, is apt to keep our minds waking with a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſenſe of our Duty, to make us indeavour after Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and ſtudy to conform our ſelves to the likeneſs and reſemblance of ſo excellent a Being, to deſire to pleaſe him by the practice of thoſe Duties which have the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Congruity and Agreement with the Wiſdom, Juſtice, and Goodneſs of his Nature, and which Reaſon and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion do both of them equally call for at our han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s.</p>
            <p>It is unreaſonable to praiſe and magnifie the Name of God, for the Works of his Hands, or for the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Providence, unleſs we do alſo indeavour to imitate thoſe Perfections which we pretend ſo highly to approve; it is a contradiction to pretend to truſt in him in our wants, or flye to him for ſuccour in a dangerous time, and yet at the ſame time to be guilty of any baſe Deſign, or to uſe any unworthy or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable means to free our ſelves from want, or to deliver our ſelves from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; when we pray to him, we do it upon ſuppoſition of his Goodneſs, that he is ready to forgive, and eaſie to be intreated, and that he is as able as he is willing to help us; but now it would not only be unreaſonable and unjuſt, but it would alſo be impudent and impious into the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to expect that God ſhould be kind and merciful to us, when we our ſelves are unmerciful to ſuch as are in want, unjuſt to thoſe with whom we Correſpond or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106412:8"/> Traffick, inflexible and inexorable to ſuch as have offended; and laſtly, when he injoyns us to repent us of our Sins, and to acknowledge and bewail them in his preſence, to make him the Confeſſor of all our actions, who is a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to them, and will one day ſit in Judgment upon them and us; the meaning of it is, that we may not be hardned in an obſtinate courſe of ſin, but that our minds by Confeſſion and Repentance may preſerve or produce in themſelves a tenderneſs for Virtue, a ſhame for the paſt enormities of our Lives, and a ſteady purpoſe and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Future to behave our ſelves ſo as is moſt for our own trueſt Intereſt, and for the Peace and quiet of the World.</p>
            <p>Nay, when in Scripture he is ſo ſevere and terrible in his Menaces againſt Idolatry, when he commands us ſo frequently and ſo expreſly not to worſhip any ſtrange God, or any Creature like our ſelves, or any painted Image, or carved Repreſentation, not to fall down to Stocks and Stones, to Silver Shrines, or Wooden Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes, or to the Garlick and Onions of <hi>Egypt,</hi> when he is ſo jealous of his Glory, and will by no means give his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to another; the meaning of all this at the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, is, not that God ſtands in need of our Worſhip, that we can add any thing to him by our Praiſes or our Prayers; or that when we are guilty of Spiritual Fornication, by going a Whoring after ſtrange Gods, or by placing the incommunicable Acts of Worſhip upon any other Object beſides himſelf, he ſuffers or loſes any thing by the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, for he cannot be more or leſs happy than he is, he was happy and perfect in the Senſe and Contemplation of his own Bleſſed Nature for Millions of Ages before the World was made; and he may ſay to us, as he did out of the Whirlewind to his Servant <hi>Job, Where waſt thou when I laid the Foundations of the Earth, when the morning
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106412:8"/> ſtars ſang together, and all the Sons of God ſhouted for joy?</hi> He reaps no advantage from our Worſhip, or our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; and <hi>if he were an hungry he would not tell us,</hi> for he is all-ſufficient in himſelf, and <hi>all the beaſts of the Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt are his, and ſo are the Cattel upon a thouſand Hills, he knows all the Fowls of the Mountains, and the wild Beaſts of the Field are in his ſight.</hi> What is the Reaſon therefore why God is ſo jealous of his Honour? ſo zealous for the incommunicable Reſpect which is due to him from all his Rational Creatures? Why, the true and only Reaſon is, That God himſelf is the moſt Noble Object our thoughts can poſſibly entertain themſelves upon, and we ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways find our ſelves moſt happy in the raviſhing Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of ſo bright, ſo lovely, ſo beautiful a Being; the conſideration of his Attributes will produce in us large and generous Thoughts, a perfect hatred of every thing that is Wicked, and a contempt of every thing that is Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and Mean; and, in a word, it will create in us, together with a Love and Admiration of him, a Breathing after him, and a deſire to be like him.</p>
            <p>But on the contrary, the Reaſon why Idolatry and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition are ſo ſeverely prohibited and forbidden, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are apt to produce quite contrary Effects upon the Lives and Manners of Men. For the practice of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry is either owing to an Opinion that God himſelf is pent up in ſome remote corner of the World, but is not always preſent in the midſt of us; that he is not intimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly twiſted into our moſt ſecret thoughts, and a Witneſs to our darkeſt and moſt concealed retirements, otherwiſe we ſhould have no need to worſhip him by any Repreſentation, when he is preſent himſelf; or elſe it is founded in a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that God of himſelf will not at all times do for us whatever is beſt and moſt reaſonable to be done, but that he relies in a manner upon the advice of others, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106412:9"/> that he is an eaſie Being, governed by Court-Favourites and Minions that are about his Perſon, otherwiſe it would be very fooliſh, though they could hear and anſwer us, which they cannot do, to have recourſe to the intereſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion either of Saints or Angels: It conſiſts on both ſides in a poor and pitiful Opinion of the Divine Nature, which muſt needs produce a proportionable Coldneſs and Indifference in us, to reſemble ſo eaſie and ſo little a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It eſtranges us from the Life of God, by making us ſtrangers to his Attributes and his Nature, and by fixing our Thoughts and our Worſhip upon finite, fading, and corporeal Objects, inſtead of an Immortal, Infinite, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>material Being.</p>
            <p>If we do not believe God to be always preſent wherever we are, and whatever we are doing, we ſhall have the leſs regard to ſubmit to his Will, or to obey his Laws, when he is either ſo remote that he cannot ſee us, or that he cannot come at us to puniſh us, if he do; and if we do believe him to be really preſent, what an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front is it, inſtead of being a Duty, to Worſhip any thing but himſelf in his Preſence? Nay, we muſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe him to be preſent, but we muſt conſtantly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to this Belief, we muſt frequently pauſe and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate upon it, that it may have the more powerful influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon our Converſations, and therefore this is the Character which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſomewhere gives of a Wicked and Unregenerate man, that <hi>he hath not God in all his thoughts.</hi> Again, If we believe God to be ſo eaſie a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he is not governed ſo much by the Equity of things, by the Reaſonableneſs of our Requeſts, or by the Conſtancy of our Obedience, or by the Sincerity of our Repentance, as by the Intereſt of Favourites, the Intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of thoſe whom he is pleaſed to call his Friends, and the Importunity of thoſe about him; if we are once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106412:9"/> that the Prayer of one Saint, and the Supereroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of another, drawn out of the imaginary Treaſury of the Church, will ſerve inſtead of Repentance and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on our parts, this muſt needs produce in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Men, a coldneſs and indifference in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of their Duty, and give great ſtrength to the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of thoſe Temptations by which Humane Nature is continually ſurrounded.</p>
            <p>And what hath been ſaid of Idolatry, is true in a very great proportion of Superſtition likewiſe. The Eſſence of Idolatry conſiſts in the Worſhip of a falſe Object; that of Superſtition in falſe and injurious Notions, concerning the true one, which hath been uſually done by one of theſe two ſeveral ways.</p>
            <p>Firſt, When Men look upon him as ſuch an eaſie Being, that he will accept of little Expiations, or of certain Rites or Ceremonies, whether of their own inventing, or of his appointment, inſtead of Repentance, Obedience, and Amendment of Life; whereas God who is infinitely concerned for the happineſs of Mankind, will accept of nothing but our reaſonable Service, and of thoſe Acts of Duty and Religion, which have a manifeſt tendency to the good of Humane Life, and to the comfort of Societies, and particular Perſons. He will not <hi>eat the Fleſh of Bulls, nor drink the Blood of Goats, but</hi> he requires that <hi>we ſhould offer unto God thankſgiving, and pay our vows unto the moſt high. To obey,</hi> in his eſteem, <hi>is better than Sacrifice, and to hearken, than the fat of Roms;</hi> and he hath ſolemnly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, That the <hi>Sacrifice of the Wicked is an abomination to him, that his Soul hateth it;</hi> and that he <hi>cannot away</hi> with the <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> and the <hi>New Moons,</hi> and the <hi>Solemn Aſſemblies,</hi> though of his own appointment, when joyned with the practice of Intemperance and Injuſtice, to the dammage and <hi>detriment,</hi> either of our ſelves or others.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106412:10"/>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of Superſtition is, when Men look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God under the Notion of a touchy and uncertain Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that is angry for nothing, and pleaſed with as little; and therefore they worſhip him with ridiculous Rites, and childiſh Expiations, to procure his Favour, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert his Diſpleaſure, and try almoſt as many, and as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Remedies againſt the anger of Heaven, as if it were the Tooth-ach, or a Tertian-Ague. And the Evil of this ſort of Superſtition conſiſts in this, That it deſtroys the Quiet and Tranquillity of Humane Life, by frighting it with cauſeleſs Fears, and imaginary Dangers, by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men perpetually ſolicitous, continually out of tune, and by producing in the habit of their minds, a Peeviſh, Fretful, Suſpicious, Diſſatisfied, Unſociable, and Unfriendly Temper.</p>
            <p>To conclude this matter, Not only the practical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Goſpel, as well as of Natural Religion, are founded in the intereſt of Mankind; but alſo the Articles of Belief, and the Miracles by which thoſe Articles were confirmed.</p>
            <p>The Articles of Belief, which I ſhall mention, are theſe two. Firſt, the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity;</hi> and Secondly, that of the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> as puzling as it is, though after all the Scoffs of the <hi>Arians</hi> of old time, and of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Hereticks of late, I do not deſpair to make it out as clearly, as any Propoſition that is never ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; I ſay, as puzling as it is, and upon Suppoſition that it were in it ſelf every whit as unintelligible, as it is pretended to be, yet thus much we know for certain, that God being an Infinite, and by Conſequence an Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Being, there may be ſome Propoſitions true concerning him, whoſe truth we that have only finite Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings cannot poſſibly comprehend; for nothing certainly can underſtand or comprehend the whole ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106412:10"/> and latitude of the Divine Nature, but the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelf; and therefore in this caſe the Counſel of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Scaliger</hi> is excellently good,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nè tu ſemper audax quaere cauſas omnium,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quaecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> libris vis prophet arum edidit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Afflata caelo, plena veraci Deo,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Operta ſacri ſupparo ſilentii,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vel tange parcus vel pudenter praeteri:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Neſcire velle quae Magiſter maximus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Docere non vult, erudita inſcitia eſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>But now if this Doctrine were not only unintelligible in it ſelf, but alſo of no uſe in common Life, to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhould it be revealed? For certainly God does not deſign in the Scripture to puzzle and confound his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to no purpoſe, but only to teach and inform them for their benefit and advantage; and therefore though the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> by reaſon that it is converſant about an Infinite Subject, cannot ſo eaſily be made out by a Finite Underſtanding; yet if we can ſhew any uſe of it, for the Benefit of Life, this is an argument to us of its truth, though it be not the Object of our Comprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And the uſe that is to be made of it in life, is this, That if we are verily perſwaded of the truth of this Doctrine, if we believe that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was not only ſent by God, but that he is really and truly God himſelf; this ought certainly to poſſeſs the Hearts of all his true Diſciples, with the greater Reverence and Eſteem for his Laws: and if we believe the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> not only to be an Effect or Emanation of the Divine Power, which is all that the <hi>Socinians</hi> underſtand by it, but that he is really and truly a Divine Perſon, that he is not barely an Attribute of God; or an Effect of the Divine Power and Will, but that he is really and truly God himſelf, we ſhall then certainly give the greater
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106412:11"/> heed to all the good Motions, and all the Virtuous Inclinations of our minds, for fear of quenching and doing deſpite to the Spirit of Grace, of doing violence to the God within us, whoſe Temples in Scripture our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are ſaid to be.</p>
            <p>And this by the way, among other very good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that have been urged againſt it, is a very good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the falſity of the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which, beſides that it is a contradiction to our Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and our Senſes, beſides that it is converſant about an Object, of which we may pretend to be Competent Judges, that is, about an Humane Body; I ſay, beſides this, though we ſhould ſuppoſe it to be true, we can aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign no uſe of it for the bettering our Lives, or for the intereſt of Mankind; but on the contrary it would be much better for us, that it ſhould be as it is, a falſe and abſurd Doctrine, becauſe the belief of it puts ſo many Indignities upon the Perſon of Chriſt, and by conſequence weakens the Authority of his Goſpel; as, that the Body of God ſhould be eaten, not only by Men, but ſometimes by Rats and Mice, and other Vermine; that in the Viſitation of the Sick, the Prieſt ſhall carry God Almighty in his Pocket, together with his Snuff-Box, his Tooth-pick, and his Tabaco; that he is champed between the Teeth, that he deſcends into the Stomach and the Bowels, and from thence into the Draught, and other very reproachful and ignominious Circumſtances, which it is a ſhame to mention; and yet this is one of the great reaſons of all the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Perſecutions, becauſe we cannot perſwade our ſelves to believe ſo impious and ſo abſurd a Doctrine as this.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Quod panem aut furfur, ſimilamve aut dona Lyaei</l>
               <l>Nolumus eſſe Deos, ſummà<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in ſede locare</l>
               <l>Myſtica quae ſacris adhibent ur pocula menſis,</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106412:11"/>
               <l>Quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſalutiferas fundunt bellaria vires;</l>
               <l>Quòd non foetenti Drvinum ſtercus ab alvo</l>
               <l>Ejicitur ſalſumque perennat ab inguine Numen;</l>
               <l>Quod Servatores noſtros non tradimus Orco,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſtophagi</hi> cives, &amp; <hi>Chriſticida</hi> Sacerdos.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>For the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied but there are Difficulties in it, though they are not ſo great neither, but that they are capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing explained, as I have endeavoured to do upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion; yet this is certain, that the belief of it muſt needs have a very potent influence upon the manners of the World, and that it is an equal Argument of the truth of this Doctrine, and of the goodneſs of God toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he hath made the performance of thoſe Duties, the Conditions of a Bleſſed Immortality in the World to come, which are our trueſt Intereſt, and our higheſt Wiſdom in this.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, For the Miracles by which the Goſpel was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, they are all of them placed in ſome Event or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that was for the advantage and benefit of the World; our Saviour went about continually doing of Good, he healed Diſeaſes, and caſt out Devils, he cleanſed the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, he reſtored the Lame and Blind to the uſe of their Feet, and of their Sight, he ſtopt running Iſſues that had been of long continuance, he bid the Sick of the Palſie riſe and walk, and he raiſed the very Dead out of their Graves, to come and give Teſtimony to the truth of his Doctrine; though it might have been perhaps an equal Confirmation of it, to have removed Mountains, or to have called the Sun out of the Firmament, or to have torn the hardeſt Rocks in ſunder; but this was not ſo ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Nature of the Doctrine it ſelf, which was all of it Calculated, as I have largely ſhewn, to promote the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106412:12"/> Intereſt and Welfare of the World.</p>
            <p>So that it being ſo undeniably clear that all the Duties, whether of Natural or of Revealed Religion, are placed in the Welfare and Happineſs of Mankind; give me leave to ſhew you that this is no Digreſſion, by applying it to the Subject we are ingaged in, concerning Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or Non-reſiſtance to the Supreme Power; and if the Miſchiefs of Reſiſtance ſhall appear to be greater, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a juſt and impartial Survey of the whole Matter than thoſe of Arbitrary Power, and in any other caſe there is no need of Reſiſtance, then it follows plainly, that Reſiſtance is in all Caſes unlawful. Wherefore to make ſhort work of the matter, If any Man will ſhew me, or will ſo much as dare to ſhew his Face, and look as if he would pretend to ſhew me, that ever a quarter of ſo much Blood was ſplit, ſo many Properties invaded, ſo many Eſtates confiſcate, by the Arbitrary Power and Humour of any Lawful Prince, as in the memory of many that are here preſent, in the laſt Civil War, then I will be content to laugh for company with <hi>Julian the Apoſtate,</hi> and ſcoff at Paſſive Obedience, as much as he hath done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caiaphas</hi> being High Prieſt uttered a Prophetick ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it ſeems in virtue of his Office, That <hi>it was expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that one man ſhould dye for the People.</hi> For ſo St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>Joh.</hi> XI. from <hi>49th</hi> to the <hi>51ſt. Caiaphas being the High-Prieſt that year, ſaid unto them, Ye know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, nor conſider that it is expedient for us, that one man ſhould dye for the People, and that the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on periſh not. And this ſpake he not of himſelf, but being High-Prieſt that year he propheſied that</hi> Jeſus <hi>ſhould dye for that nation.</hi> Which words though in their Prophetick meaning, they did refer to the Expiatory Sacrifice of the Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus</hi> upon the Croſs for our Sins; yet it is plain that the reaſon of them is grounded upon this Maxim,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106412:12"/> that the Intereſt of a Nation is to be preferred before the Intereſt or Wellfare of one man. <hi>It is expedient for us that one Man ſhould dye for the People, and that the whole nation periſh not.</hi> So that we have here a ſure word of Prophecy, that is the Teſtimony of God himſelf, that a greater Intereſt of Mankind is to be preferred before a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer; for what is here affirmed of one Man, with relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the whole People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the ſame holds in its proportion, and in the Reaſon of it of any leſſer number, with reference to a greater. From whence it follows plainly, though I am by no means a Friend to Arbitrary Government, and though, God be thanked, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo Merciful and Juſt a Prince, whoſe Goodneſs is the only thing that is exceſſive in him, we have no manner of occaſion to defend it; I ſay, from hence it follows plainly, that it is unlawful, becauſe a few Men ſuffer in their Fortunes or their Lives, by the Cruelty and Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of an Arbitrary Power, for the People to take up Arms, to protect themſelves againſt it; becauſe the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties and Deſolations of War are incomparably greater than thoſe of an unjuſt or an unmerciful Prince: And therefore, if God Almighty may be allowed to be a more competent Judge in the Caſe, than the Author of <hi>Julian the Apoſtate,</hi> it is much better for the People to be quiet.</p>
            <p>I know, the barbarous Perſecutions of the Primitive Chriſtians will be urged in this Caſe, they being ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous as they were, ſo cruelly perſecuted, ſo barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly tormented, and for ſo good a Cauſe, meerly for Believing and Embracing that Doctrine which taught nothing but what was for the good of the Perſecutors themſelves; and becauſe the juſt and full ſtating of this matter, is a thing of great importance to the true deciding of the Queſtion under Debate,</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:106412:13"/>
            <p>Therefore, I ſhall conſider in the Firſt Place, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact; and,</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Behaviour of the Chriſtians under it: and,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Reaſon upon which that Behaviour was founded.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For the Matter of Fact, it is unqueſtionably cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That the Perſecution upon the Chriſtians, for many Ages, was very heavy and cruel, which our Saviour fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw before he left the World, and therefore took care to arm them by his Doctrine againſt it, bidding them not fear thoſe that could kill the Body, and pronouncing a Bleſſing upon all thoſe that ſuffered Perſecution for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake: And <hi>Pliny</hi> himſelf, who was <hi>Proconſul</hi> of <hi>Bithynia,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Trajan,</hi> confeſſes, in a Letter to his Maſter upon that occaſion, which is ſtill extant, that he was weary of tormenting them; but yet after all, I love to give the Devil his due: and becauſe I would not ſo much as imply or inſinuate any thing meerly to defend a Cauſe which is not true, therefore I ſhall preſume to ſay, That the Perſecution of the Primitive Chriſtians was neither ſo great, nor ſo unjuſt, as it is commonly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented. And Firſt, I ſay, it was not ſo great, and I give theſe Reaſons for my Opinion:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Writers of thoſe times, who have given us the accounts we have of thoſe Perſecutions, have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly exaggerated and aggravated the matter beyond the truth of things; and this among others was the peculiar Fault of <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> with Relation to <hi>Julian the Apoſtate,</hi> rather to ſhew his Wit, and to expoſe a Paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and Ungovernable mind, than that <hi>Julian</hi> deſerved ſuch uſage at his hands, who, bating that he was no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, was otherwiſe as Wiſe and Virtuous, and in all points as Gallant and as excellent a Prince as ever wielded Scepter, or ſat upon a Throne.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106412:13"/>
            <p>Another thing is, That the <hi>Romans</hi> at the firſt were ſo little acquainted with the Chriſtians, that they fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently called them by the name of <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo ſaith <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius, Judaeos impulſore Chreſto tumultuantes;</hi> where by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Vit. Claud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Judaei,</hi> or the <hi>Jews,</hi> it is manifeſt the Followers of <hi>Chriſt</hi> were underſtood, ſo that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were lookt upon only as a Sect or Faction among the <hi>Jews,</hi> of which <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the head. Nay, ſo little were the <hi>Romans</hi> acquainted with the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that they did not ſo much as know his Name; for in this very Citation they call him <hi>Chreſtus,</hi> which is as much as to ſay, <hi>the Good,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Chriſtus,</hi> which is as much as <hi>the Anointed,</hi> and anſwers to the <hi>Hebrew Maſhiach,</hi> or <hi>the Meſſias;</hi> and ſo little did they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See my Lord of</hi> Cheſter <hi>in his Book upon the Creed, upon the Article,</hi> And in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</note> underſtand the Religion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that it was commonly believed among them, that the <hi>Jews</hi> worſhipped an Aſſes Head, and that <hi>Pompey</hi> ſound nothing elſe when he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to enter into the Holy of Holies; and yet why they ſhould perſecute the <hi>Jews</hi> for this, any more than they did the <hi>Egyptians</hi> for the Worſhip of the <hi>Ibis</hi> and the <hi>Crocodile,</hi> and ſuch like Monſters, I do not underſtand; and it is certain that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> did Worſhip theſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in <hi>Domitians</hi> time, if we will believe <hi>Juvenal</hi> who wrote in it; for ſo he tells us,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>—<hi>Neſcis Voluſi Bithynice, qualia demens</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aegyptus Portenta colit? Crocodilon adorat</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pars haec, illa colit ſaturam ſerpentibus</hi> Ibin.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>But the true Reaſon why the <hi>Jews</hi> were Perſecuted, was not becauſe of their Religion, but becauſe they were looked upon as a Rebellious People, as indeed they were; and ſo are their Brother <hi>Sabbatarians</hi> now a-days; and the Chriſtians being lookt upon only as a Sect or Faction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106412:14"/> the <hi>Jews,</hi> they were accounted as Enemies to the Empire, and all that ſided with them, or eſpouſed the Cauſe and Intereſt of Chriſtianity, were looked upon as taking part with their Enemies: Nay, the <hi>Jews</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves repreſented the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> as Enemies to <hi>Caſar;</hi> and therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> adviſes them to remove this Scandal, and let the World ſee how much the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had been miſrepreſented, by Patience and Obedience. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man, for the Lords ſake, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be to the King as Supreme, or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him, for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well: For ſo is the will of God, that with well-doing ye may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi> So that it is plain upon the whole matter, that the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were not at firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from one another by the <hi>Romans;</hi> that the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were perſecuted under the notion of <hi>Jews,</hi> and that the <hi>Jews</hi> were oppreſt as Enemies to the State, not upon a Religious but a Political account: Nay, they were ſo far from being prohibited the exerciſe of their Religion, that in <hi>Domitian</hi>'s time there were places ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for their Publick Worſhip, as is evident by this paſſage of <hi>Juvenal;</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic, ubi Nocturnae</hi> Numa <hi>conſtituebat amicae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nunc ſacri fontis nemus &amp; delubra locantur</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Judaeis. Quorum Cophinus foenum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſupellex.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>But yet at this very time they were oppreſſed and kept under by the <hi>Romans</hi> to that degree, that all the Nation were in a manner Beggars; for ſo it follows in the very next words of that Poet,</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Omnis eim populo mercedem pendere Juſſa eſt</l>
               <l>Arbor &amp; ejectis mendicat ſylva camoenis.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106412:14"/>
            <p>And in another place,
<q>
                  <l>Arcanam Judaea tremens mendicat in aurem,</l>
               </q> And in another,
<q>
                  <l>Ede ubi conſiſtas, in qua te quaero proſeuchâ?</l>
               </q> They were Vagabonds and Straglers all over the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and got their living in a great meaſure by playing the Gypſies, and by telling of Fortunes; from whence the word <hi>Chaldaeus,</hi> which denotes any Inhabitant of <hi>Paleſtine</hi> or <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> is uſed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Authors, for a Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning man, or a Fortune-Teller; and the Oracle uſes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for the ſame ſort of Men,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q> Nay, after the reception of Chriſtianity in it, they were ſtill looked upon as dangerous to the Empire, as appears by ſeveral Laws againſt them, ſtill extant in the <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Code,</hi> under the Title <hi>de Judaeis, Coelicolis, &amp; Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanis;</hi> and beſides that they were a ſtubborn and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous People, they were looked upon as a very vicious Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple likewiſe, as appears by a paſſage of <hi>Martial,</hi> who at once lays Perjury, and another ſmall fault of <hi>Salamanca,</hi> to the charge of a <hi>Jew:</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Paedicas puerum, verpe poeta, meum:</l>
               <l>Ecce, negas, juraſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mihi per templa Tonantis;</l>
               <l>Non credo, jura, verpe, per Anchialum.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Nay, they were under ſo great Hatred and Deteſtation all over the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, that to conceal themſelves
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106412:15"/> they uſed ſeveral tricks to repair the Defects that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion had made: And as from their being Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed they were called <hi>Verpi;</hi> ſo from this new Device, which ſeveral Laws were enacted to prohibit, they were called <hi>recutiti;</hi> and ſo <hi>Martial</hi> uſes <hi>recutita colla boum;</hi> for the Necks of Oxen that had been skinned over again, after they had been galled by the Yoke; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes to this Cuſtom, in the <hi>7th</hi> Chapter of the Firſt to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>Is any man called being circumciſed? let him not become uncircumciſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude this matter, if we conſider the famous Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> which is uſually produced to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the Meekneſs and Patience of the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, where he tells the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, <hi>omnia veſtra implevimus,</hi> That the Court and Camp, the Cities, Towns, and Villages, the Markets and Exchanges, and Courts of Judicature, were all of them full of Chriſtians; if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon that paſſage in the Life of <hi>Jovian,</hi> where when he refuſed to be the Emperour of <hi>Pagans,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, after the Death of <hi>Julian,</hi> all of them unanimouſly declared themſelves to be Chriſtians; if we ſurvey the Vaults and Places under Ground, that are at this day to be ſeen at <hi>Rome,</hi> the deſcription of which was publiſhed, not long ago, by the Writers of the <hi>Roma Subterranea,</hi> where <note place="margin">v. Rom. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr. L. 1. c. 2. ſ. 17. &amp; in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numento Sepule brali Alex. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyris, in Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rio Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſti.</note> the Chriſtians buried their Dead, and where, it is certain, they were uſed to Aſſemble; theſe places could neither be built without publick notice, neither was it poſſible for the Chriſtians to meet together in them ſo privately, as not to be diſcerned. All which are very ſtrong Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that Chriſtianity, though it were oppreſt at ſome times, yet it had its lucid intervals, and was connived at at others; and that at the ſame time when it was Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and Oppreſt, yet there were many that lived quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Profeſſion of it, and enjoyed places of Honour
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106412:15"/> and Profit into the Bargain; but yet I do not deny that at ſome times eſpecially the Perſecution was very Bloody, and that the Patience and Courage of the Chriſtians ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to vye for Maſtery with the Barbarity and Fierceneſs of their Tormentors, inſomuch that the Governours of the Church themſelves were forced to make Laws on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to reſtrain the too forward Zeal of ſuch as were Ambitious and Covetous of being <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the Second place, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Perſecutions were not altogether ſo great, ſo neither were they altogether ſo unreaſonable or unjuſt, as they have been uſually but falſly repreſented. I do not mean that any Power on Earth hath a right of Perſecuting the true Religion, and a Religion that is ſo plainly founded in the Intereſt of Mankind; but the thing was this:</p>
            <p>The People that profeſſed Chriſtianity increaſed ſo faſt, and withdrew themſelves in ſo great Numbers from the publick Aſſemblies, into private Meetings by themſelves, that this was looked upon, as it deſerved, by the <hi>Roman</hi> Government, with a very ſuſpicious Eye, as a matter of very dangerous Conſequence to the <hi>Imperial</hi> Eagles, whoſe Wings were like to be clipt by the prevailing Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of a growing Party, who withdrew themſelves from the Publick into Corners, and what they did there, could not certainly be known by any but themſelves: and though they made never ſo large profeſſions of Patience and Humility, and of their embracing the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance; yet this was no ſecurity to the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, if ever they ſhould be ſtrong enough to ſet up for themſelves. For we may talk what we pleaſe; and though the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance be a very wholſome and a very reaſonable Doctrine, yet when a Party gets Power into their hands, it is hardly to be ſuppoſed but they will certainly uſe it to the endangering the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106412:16"/> Rights of Princes, and the Peace of the State.</p>
            <p>If you ask, why the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours did not rather turn Chriſtians in this Caſe, that ſo they might ſecure this growing Party to themſelves? To this it is to be anſwered, That beſides the Prejudices which they had imbibed from their Education in the <hi>Pagan</hi> Superſtition, it was at firſt againſt the Intereſt of the State to do it, becauſe the <hi>Pagan</hi> Party was more numerous; ſo that in probability by declaring for Chriſtianity, they muſt have loſt their Empire, and their lives together; but afterwards when Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty got to ſuch an head, that the torrent was no longer to be reſiſted or ſtem'd; then <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> rather out of Reaſon of State, than for the ſake of the Fabulous Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rition of the Croſs, found himſelf obliged to turn a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            <p>Another very great inconvenience that always goes along with any Party that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>parates from the Government, is this, That though the Principles of a Party be never ſo peaceable, yet this is certain, they love themſelves better than thoſe that are of another Perſwaſion, and they have a kindneſs for any man that ſides with them, and takes their part, and therefore they are commonly made uſe of by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented and Ambitious Men, to work their Deſigns upon the State, under Religious Pretences, which bad men do ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily make, and weak men do as eaſily embrace, when there is an appearance of ſtrength, that they are like to go through with their buſineſs. From whence it follows plainly, that all Separation from the publick Worſhip, is abſolutely unlawful, unleſs in ſuch Caſes where the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment impoſes ſuch terms of Communion, as are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Honour of God, and the Happineſs of Men, which I have ſhewn already to be the Caſe of Idolatry; and by conſequence, the Primitive Chriſtians are excuſed, though the Diſſenters of our times are not,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106412:16"/> and therefore it is more juſt to make and execute laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, than it was againſt the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of old; and we may take it for granted, for it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly true, that the Separation from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was the true cauſe of that late horrid and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Plot, with which the Government was in ſo great danger of being overturned; for the Conſpirators would never have dared to lay ſo deteſtable and wicked a Deſign, had they not known there was a numerous Party that would have ſtood by them when they had done; and though I am not ſo fooliſhly uncharitable to believe, but that moſt of the Diſſenters knew nothing of the Deſign, yet it is certain, that had it taken Effect, they would have ſided with the Conſpirators againſt the Laws, the Monarchy, and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by which they think themſelves to be Oppreſt, and this without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was the great incouragement to the Conſpirators, as well to enter upon the Deſign at firſt, as to proceed ſo far in it as they did; and I am really of Opinion we ſhall never be free from a Plot in ſome proportion; if not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Life of the King, yet againſt the Peace and Honour of his Government, ſo long as there is one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle in <hi>England</hi> remaining.</p>
            <p>Another thing, which though it cannot make the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of good men, and of a good Religion Lawful, yet it may in part excuſe, and juſtify the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours for what they did, is, That the Chriſtians were repreſented to them as a ſort of Lewd, Vicious, and Debauch'd People, that in their Aſſemblies they practiſed a promiſcuous Luſt, and polluted themſelves with inceſtuous Copulations, which though it were moſt ſcandalouſly falſe of ſuch as were truly and in reallity Chriſtians, yet it was but too true of many that were accounted of the number, ſuch as the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> were, and the lewd Followers of <hi>Baſilides,</hi> and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106412:17"/> 
               <hi>Valentinus,</hi> of whom it is enough to make a Mans Ears tingle, and his Hair ſtand an end, to read thoſe lewd Stories which <hi>Ephiphanius</hi> and <hi>Ireneus</hi> have reported; and it is certain, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws were not more ſevere againſt any thing, than againſt the practice of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Luſt, inſomuch that by the old Laws and Uſages of the Empire, all the degrees prohibited in Marriage, which, by the <hi>Moſaick</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, ſeem to me <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Authen. Col. h. 9. tit. 36. l. 154. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaic, &amp; Rom. Leg. 1. Collat. tit de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſlis Nupt. p. 90. C. Theod. l. 3. tit. 12. l.</hi> 14.</note> to have been exactly the ſame, were puniſhed with Death; and this was the Sanction of a <hi>Novel</hi> of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> ſtill extant, and directed to the Inhabitants of <hi>Oſdroena</hi> and <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> and of another of <hi>Dioeletian</hi> and <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian,</hi> in the Fragments of <hi>Pythaeus;</hi> and it appears by a Law of <hi>Arcadius,</hi> and <hi>Honorius,</hi> in the <hi>Theodoſian Code,</hi> whereby the Marriage of <hi>Couſin Germans,</hi> is diſpenſed with, that the puniſhment for the ſaid Marriages, in the time of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> was no leſs than <hi>ignium &amp; proſcriptionis,</hi> both the Parties were to be burnt alive, and their Eſtates to be Confiſcate; ſo that upon ſuppoſition that they did really believe ſuch horrid Impieties to have been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed amongſt them, as they were among ſome that went under the notion of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> it is no wonder that the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws were ſo ſevere againſt them.</p>
            <p>Another thing, which though it cannot juſtifie the Perſecution of the Chriſtians, yet it may render it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what leſs Barbarous and Unjuſt, than otherwiſe it would appear to be, is, That their over-forward, and over-heated Zeal was ſuch, that they were not content according to their Duty, barely to ſtick to the profeſſion of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, without affronting and reviling the <hi>Pagan</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Idolatry, upon all occaſions; and though I know not what others may think, yet I am of this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion till I am better informed, that if I ſhould take a Voyage to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to pick a quarrel with the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106412:17"/> 
               <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> and revile <hi>Mahomet</hi> for an <hi>Impoſtor;</hi> or to <hi>Rome,</hi> to take his <hi>Holineſs</hi> by the Beard, and call him <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and <hi>Scarlet</hi> Whore, and if for my pains I ſhould be condemned by the one to the Gallies, or by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to the Inquiſition, it would be very idle in this caſe for me to complain of Perſecution, or to comfort my ſelf with ſuffering for Righteouſneſs ſake; for God that hath given us expreſs leave, if we be Perſecuted in one City, to flee to another, gives us no warrant to expoſe our Perſons to unneceſſary Dangers; and beſides, the Religion of a Nation, though it be falſe, is a Sacred thing, and ought not to be affronted and rudely ſet at nought, nor to be oppoſed by any thing, but by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and Reaſon.</p>
            <p>To all which it is to be added, That the <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, though they were indeed, eſpecially ſome of them, very Cruel and Inhumane towards their Chriſtian Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, yet all the Cruelties and Indignities which they ſuffered, are not to be imputed to the Emperours and the Laws, but to the Rage and Fury of Idolatrous Bigots, and of an incenſed Rabble: As for Example, It is Death by the Laws of this Nation, for a Popiſh Prieſt to be ſeen upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground, and it would be very well if it were ſo for a Non-conforming one too; but yet, if a man in the Streets being taken or ſuſpected for a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt, ſhall without the formality of a Legal Proceſs be torn in pieces by the Rabble, this is not to be imputed to the King and the Laws, when they could not have prevented it, though they would never ſo fain.</p>
            <p>To ſumm up all that I have to ſay upon this point; As for the laſt Perſecution under <hi>Julian the Apoſtate,</hi> if it may be called a Perſecution, for it was but very gentle in compariſon of the others; to ſpeak a plain Truth, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of thoſe times, who were very turbulent,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106412:18"/> though not altogether ſo bad as our True Proteſtants are now a days, may thank themſelves for putting the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour upon an apparent neceſſity, if he would ſit ſafe upon the Throne, to oppreſs them; for the encouragement and countenance given to Chriſtianity by the two laſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and his Son <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> had very miſchievous Effects upon the World, inſtead of doing a Service to it, which it is the Deſign of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to do; but by the Paſſions and interfering Intereſts and Deſigns of men, it ſo happened, that the Factions between the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and the <hi>Arians,</hi> and <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> grew ſo high, that they ſhook the Empire, and threatned to tear the World in pieces; and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> who had before eſpouſed the Intereſt of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and it is probable would not have relinquiſht it for no reaſon, ſaw no humane means ſo likely to ſettle and eſtabliſh Peace in the Empire, as by diſcountenancing all the ſeveral Factions, and indeavouring to reduce again the <hi>Catholick</hi> Unity of the <hi>Pagan</hi> Superſtition; and this, if I am not miſtaken, is the great myſtery of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion at this day, it was deſigned and calculated to compound the buſineſs betwixt the Chriſtians and the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans,</hi> to make all quiet, and to bring them both under the Popes Juriſdiction. For it is manifeſt that in that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there are many Rites and Practices that are of the growth of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and notwithſtanding the footing which Chriſtianity had gotten in the World, the <hi>Pagan</hi> Faction was powerful in the Empire, as low as <hi>Juſtinian</hi>'s <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Linden. brog. Cod. l. l. Antiq. p.</hi> 938.</note> and in the <hi>Capitulars</hi> of <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> which are a great deal later, there are Laws againſt <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and againſt the eating of things ſacrificed to Idols, ſtill to be met with; which Laws would not only have been needleſs, but ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous alſo, upon ſuppoſition that <hi>Paganiſm</hi> had been no where to be found in his Dominions.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:106412:18"/>
            <p>But let that be as it will, I am very confident that the account of <hi>Julian</hi>'s Perſecution, is wholly to be aſcribed to the Cauſe I have mentioned; and to the ſhame, not of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, but of ſuch as called themſelves Chriſtians, be it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that as their Diviſions ſhook the Empire in the time of <hi>Conſtantine, Conſtantius,</hi> and <hi>Julian,</hi> ſo afterwards they broke it utterly in pieces, they brought in the <hi>Goths,</hi> and other barbarous Nations into <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Saracens</hi> into <hi>Greece;</hi> and we are as much obliged to the True Proteſtants of old for the Siege firſt of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> and at this preſent time of <hi>Vienna,</hi> as we are to thoſe that are now, for their good Wiſhes, and pious E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jaculations, that the ſtrongeſt Bulwark of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> may be taken.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with the Firſt Point, the matter of Fact, as to the Perſecution of the Primitive Chriſtians: I ſhall not have time to finiſh all the particulars which I propoſed to my ſelf to diſcourſe upon, and therefore I ſhall only beg upon this ſolemn occaſion, that you would give me ſo much of your Patience, that I may finiſh this point of Non-reſiſtance, that ſo you may ſee the more plainly, what your Duty is, and by the practice of it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs your thankfulneſs to God for your Deliverance.</p>
            <p>The Second thing to be conſidered is, how the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans behaved themſelves under the Perſecutions which they ſuffered. And to this I ſhall only anſwer in ſhort, That they ſubmitted to the greateſt ſeverities that could be uſed againſt them, that they ſubmitted to them all with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken Conſtancy, and a miraculous Patience; that they were ſo far from reſiſting the Emperours, that they prayed for them, for the Health and Wellfare of their Perſons, for the ſucceſs of their Affairs, for peace within their Walls, and plenteouſneſs within their Palaces, and for the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Iſſue of all their Warlike Enterprizes, and Atchieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106412:19"/> they drew their Swords for their Defence and Honour, and ſerved in their Armies, and were ſo nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in them, that they had the Empire in a manner at their diſpoſal, and yet never offered to lift up an hand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, after all the Provocations, Cruelties, and Indignities that had been put upon them; but becauſe the <hi>late Writer</hi> of <hi>Julian the Apoſtate</hi> makes it a different Caſe in <hi>Julian</hi>'s time, from what it was before, and that the Chriſtians might then have lawfully ſtood up in the defence of themſelves, though they could not do it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and becauſe he indeavours to bring the parallel home to our own Doors, therefore you ſhall give me leave, as becomes a good Subject, and a Faithful Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and as the Solemnity of this occaſion requires, to lay the impudence and unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of that profligate Wretch, and mercenary Scribler, very briefly, and yet very plainly before you.</p>
            <p>The difference of the Caſe which he makes to have been betwixt the Chriſtians in <hi>Julian</hi>'s time, and thoſe that lived before him, is this, That in <hi>Julian</hi>'s time, his two immediate Predeceſſors, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> had eſtabliſhed Chriſtianity in the Empire, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Laws of the Empire were on the Chriſtians ſide, ſo that they could not be perſecuted but againſt Law, and by conſequence might lawfully defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>This is the ſtreſs of his Argument fairly repreſented; and in my Anſwer to it, I ſhall conſider:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether the thing it ſelf, which he lays down, and takes for granted, is true, that the Laws of the Empire in <hi>Julian</hi>'s time were on the Chriſtians ſide.</p>
            <p>And, Secondly, I ſhall, as he does, bring the matter home, and conſider the Caſe of altering the Succeſſion, and of Obedience to a Popiſh Succeſſor, if any ſuch, for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106412:19"/> for the ſins of this Nation, ſhould by Gods juſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be allowed to reign over us.</p>
            <p>And firſt, I do abſolutely and poſitively deny that the Laws of the Empire were or could be on the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſide, when <hi>Julian</hi> himſelf was againſt them; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Government was abſolute, and conſequently the Will of the preſent Emperour was the only Law they had: Therefore the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours were ſometimes called in <hi>Greek,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and at other times, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both of which terms do ſignifie <hi>an abſolute Lord;</hi> and there is an Appendix to the <hi>Code</hi> and <hi>Pandects</hi> of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> which is for that reaſon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>the Authentiques,</hi> that is to ſay, the Laws or Edicts of an Arbitrary and Uncontroulable Prince.</p>
            <p>The Body of the Civil-Law, which was publiſhed by <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> conſiſts wholly either of the Opinions of ſuch as were accounted the beſt <hi>Roman</hi> Lawyers, which had their Force and Obligation from the <hi>Imperial Sanction,</hi> or of the Reſcripts or Letters of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours to the Governours of Provinces and of Cities, and to the Pretors or Judges of the Law, and a deciſion of any Caſe under the Emperours hand, was every whit as good and indiſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Law, as an Act of Parliament is amongſt us; nay, the Senate were ſo far from having any ſhare in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment with him, that they are expoſed by the <hi>Roman</hi> 
               <note place="margin">C. Th. lib 6. tit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l, 14. &amp; ib tit. 4. l. 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> v. etia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. Theod. tit. 1. &amp; 2. &amp;c. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſ. l. 1. tit. 4. l. de reſponſis pru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>entum, &amp; l. 2. tit, 1. l 12. &amp; l. 4. tit. 11. l 2.</note> Satyriſtfor their Servility and Slavery to the <hi>Caeſars;</hi> and I remember particularly in the <hi>Theodoſian Code,</hi> there are ſeveral Laws directed to the Senate, and the time when they were read publickly amongſt them, in order to their being obeyed, was entered down in the Regiſters or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moires of the Houſe, which were as exact as the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of our Parliaments are now a-days. And one of the firſt things in the Volume of <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> is to aſſert and vindicate the Imperial Authority, both in the making
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106412:20"/> of Laws, and in the interpretation of them if any doubt <note place="margin">v. Praeſat. Cod. de no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o lodice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aciendo.</note> ſhould ariſe, which he decrees by virtue of his Arbitrary and Supream Authority to be wholly locked up in the Breaſt of the Emperour.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, It is plain that there were three ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewals of the <hi>Roman</hi> Law, by the command of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, <note place="margin">v. Jac. Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throfred prolegom in C. Th.</note> and the Volumes that were publiſhed received their Authority wholly and intirely from the Imperial Sanction or Decree; the firſt of theſe Reviewals was in the time of <hi>Adrian</hi> the Succeſſor of <hi>Trajan,</hi> the ſecond in that of <hi>Theodoſius the younger,</hi> and the third in that of <hi>Juſtinian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let any man judge what truth there is in the bold Affirmation of this unskilful Dabler in the Civil Law, that the Laws of the Empire were on the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſide, at the ſame time when the Emperour himſelf was againſt them, and when the Will of the Emperour was the only Law of the Empire; it would be eaſie to prove, and it hath been done to excellent purpoſe already, not only that he is no more a good Civilian, than he is a good Subject, or an honeſt Man, but that he hath ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and <hi>Bracton,</hi> and <hi>Fleta,</hi> and <hi>Cooke</hi> upon <note place="margin">v. <hi>Dr.</hi> Hicks <hi>in his</hi> Jovian.</note> 
               <hi>Littleton,</hi> and the <hi>Judges Reports,</hi> and <hi>Ruled Caſes,</hi> to as little purpoſe as he hath done his Bible.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Julian</hi> were a Perſecutor of Chriſtianty, ſo were his Officers, and the Governours of the Provinces likewiſe, which they could neither do nor juſtifie without Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from him, which Authority was conveyed without Queſtion in the uſual manner by the Imperial Reſcripts, or Letters, and if there are none of them extant at this day, this is no Argument that there never were any ſuch Laws, but only that afterwards they were repealed, and therefore in thoſe Collections of the Civil Law, which were publiſhed afterwards by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Juſtinian,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106412:20"/> they were omitted as uſeleſs, or rather they could not be inſerted without remaining ſtill to the prejudice of Chriſtianity in their former Force and Obligation.</p>
            <p>And after all, the behaviour of the Chriſtians towards <hi>Julian,</hi> though it were, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s it ſeems, more mutinous and diſorderly than in former times, yet nothing appears that ever they did actually Conſpire againſt him, much leſs that they ſpoke the Epilogue to <hi>Julian the Apoſtate,</hi> as our <hi>True Proteſtants</hi> were about to do; for whether the Author deſigned it or no, the Book was exactly fitted to prepare the minds of the People for the Rebellion that was to follow, and they that ſet him on work, did cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly intend it for that purpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <p>And what is it, I beſeech you, that he produces to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the matter of Fact, that the Chriſtians were leſs O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to <hi>Julian</hi> than to former Emperours; why he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces ſeveral Witneſſes for it, and very fine Witneſſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are; there was a paſſionate Old Gentleman <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi>'s Father, there were three or four an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Women that ſat talking together at their Needle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k in a Window, there were the <hi>Antiochians,</hi> who were got into the way of <hi>Pafquils</hi> and <hi>Lampoons,</hi> and were very much degenerated from their Predeceſſors, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom the Scripture tells us the Believers were firſt called <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and there was <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who brings up the rear with a bun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le of <hi>Greek</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ations made alter <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hearing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he had a mind at once to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>neſs of his Wit, and the ſmallneſs of his Diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tion together, and all that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe People did, was only that they murmured and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pln<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and gave the Emperour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Language and Ill Wiſhes, but they went no further, only the <hi>Old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an</hi> was on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, as it ſhould ſeem, to <hi>kick</hi> his Royal Maſter, which of an <hi>Old Man</hi> was couraglouſly meant, and ſome
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106412:21"/> body had ſo little wit to tell Poſterity the Story, by which he did at once expoſe the Biſhop, and magnifie the Vertue and the Patience of the Emperour, who could put up ſuch Indignities in the mideſt of his Idolatry with a Chriſtian temper, and without that juſt revenge which they deſerved.</p>
            <p>But does it appear that ever the Chriſtians of that Age reſiſted him, or took up Arms againſt him, or that the generality of them, when we have ſet aſide, a few paſſionate and Seditious Fellows, did talk ſo lewdly and ſo ſcandalouſly concerning him? No; but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it appears, that in his laſt Expedition the generality of his Army were Chriſtians; and it cannot be ſuppoſed otherwiſe, if the Chriſtians were ſo numerous in <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> time, but that after the Encouragement given to Chriſtianity by two ſeveral Emperours ſucceeding one another, they were ſtill more powerful and formidable than before, and yet we know of no Sword that was ever drawn in the Quarrel, or ſo much as intended to be drawn.</p>
            <p>And ſo much concerning the nature of the <hi>Roman</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and the behaviour of the Chriſtians under it in the time of <hi>Julian;</hi> let us now briefly apply this to the Bill of Excluſion, and the Point of a Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour to the Imperial Crown of theſe Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>As for the Bill of Excluſion I ſhall not reflect upon the Perſons that were chieſly concerned in it; this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate Conſpiracy hath I hope opened the Eyes of ſome of thoſe Gentlemen that were Zealous for it; and there are others partly at the call of Nature, and partly by the ſtroke of Juſtice, that are gone to their own place; and I ſhall not inſult over any mans Calamity, or go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to diſturb the Aſhes of the Dead, but let all the Kings Enemies be as they are, unleſs they will Repent,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106412:21"/> and become Friends to themſelves as well as to their Prince, and upon that condition, let them all be forgiven and forgotten.</p>
            <p>But as for the Bill which they preferred in Parliament, though I do not meddle with the Statute of <hi>Queen Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> ſo much talked of about the Succeſſion, I do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that it was naturally unlawful for the King to paſs it, and that for theſe two Reaſons,</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe a Succeſſive Monarchy is without all queſtion the beſt Form of Government upon the Face of the Earth, it being eaſie to ſhew, if the time would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, and if it would not be too long a digreſſion, that this ſort of Polity is the leaſt expoſed to Factions, and by conſequence is the beſt fitted to procure the Peace and Happineſs of the World; and the King who is accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God for the good of his People, hath no natural right to alter, or to conſent to the alteration of the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment from a better Form of Government to a worſe, and yet this in all probability would have been the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence if that Bill had paſſed.</p>
            <p>For if an Heir may be Excluded upon one Pretence, he may alſo upon another, and they that are Enemies to Monarchy will never want Pretences till all the Line be Excluded, and the Monarchy it ſelf utterly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.</p>
            <p>But then, Secondly, ſuppoſing a ſucceſſive Monarchy to be but of equal advantage to the World with any other Form of Government whatſoever, or let us ſuppoſe it to be a little worſs, which is as much as our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries in reaſon can deſire; yet the preſent Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, meerly for that reaſon, becauſe it is the preſent, is the beſt, becauſe of the Dangers and Animoſities, the Strife and War, and Bloodſhed to which all Altera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions in Government are expoſed; and therefore it was excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106412:22"/> well adviſed of <hi>Solomon</hi> in the 24th at the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs</hi> at the 21ſt Verſe; <hi>My Son fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are givan to change:</hi> For which he gives this admirable Reaſon in the very next Verſe, <hi>For their Calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the Ruine of them both.</hi> And this ought in all Ages hereafter to be remembered to the Kings Honour, that the Dangerous and threatning importunity of a reſtleſs Faction was never able to move the Scale of Juſtice out of its Royal Ballance, or prevail with him to conſent to any thing, though in never ſo great Straits and Exigences of his Affairs, which was like to be of ſo Dangerous Conſequence to the Good of the People, as well as to the Rights of the Crown and the Royal Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives which himſelf and the Kings and Queens of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> his Anceſtors have enjoyed.</p>
            <p>May he ſtill continue to defend himſelf and us againſt the wicked Encroachments and Deſigns of Men much more Arbitrary than the Government they complain of, and as often as they Conſpire againſt his Intereſt, his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or his Life, ſo often let them be detected and exemplarily puniſh'd, and <hi>let the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rejoyce in thy ſtrength, O Lord, exceeding glad let him be of thy Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the buſineſs of Obedience to a Popiſh Suceſſour, if God in his anger ſhould ſend us ſuch an one, I ſhall now immediately have occaſion to conſider it under the third and laſt head, in which I will be very brief, and in which I have promiſed to ſhew the Reaſons upon which the paſſive behaviour of the Primitive Chriſtians was founded, which I have in part conſidered already, and ſhew'd you that the Reaſon why Obedience, even to a Perſecuting Prince, is of neceſſity required at our hands, is, Becauſe it is better for the Peace of the World, and for the Happineſs of Humane Life, that the Prince ſhould
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106412:22"/> be Arbitrary, than that the Subjects ſhould be Judges in their own Cauſe, which they are of neceſſity ſuppoſed to be in all the caſes of Reſiſtance that can be ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now only ſtrengthen what I have ſaid alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by ſome other Arguments which are more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Theological conſideration.</p>
            <p>And firſt, There was the Command of our Saviour, who Commanded his Diſciples in thoſe times of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution by no means to reſiſt their Enemies and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers in his Sermon on the Mount.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, This Doctrine of Obedience was over and over inculcated by the Apoſtles; St. <hi>Paul</hi> is ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſs to this purpoſe in the <hi>13th</hi> to the <hi>Romans, Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers, for there is no Power but of God; the Powers that be are ordained of God. Whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation; for Rulers are not a Terrour to Good works, but to the Evil; wilt thou then not be afraid of the Power, do that which is good and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame, for he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good: But if thou do that which is evil be afraid, for he beareth not the Sword in vain, for he is the Miniſter of God, a revenger to execute Wrath upon him that doeth Evil. Wherefore you muſt needs be ſubject, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake. Not only for Wrath,</hi> that is, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of a Principle of fear, <hi>but alſo for Conſcience ſake;</hi> that is, out of a Principle of Duty; which Duty I have ſhewn to be founded in the Peace and Quiet of the World, and in the Intereſt and Happineſs of Humane Life; and therefore when he tells us that <hi>he is the Miniſter of God to us for Good,</hi> we muſt allow him in the Exerciſe of his Government, to judge for himſelf what that <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> is, otherwiſe he will unavoidably <hi>bear the Sword in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106412:23"/> vain,</hi> and we ſhall never be puniſht but when we pleaſe our ſelves. So alſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> argues in the words that have been already produced, <hi>ſubmit your ſelves to every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supream, or unto Governours as unto them that are ſent by him, for the puniſhmen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well;</hi> but now if we be allowed in all Caſes to determine for our ſelves when we do <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill,</hi> ſo as they ſhall have no power to puniſh or reward, but with our own conſent, then it is we that are the Kings and the Governours, and not they.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Doctrine of Non reſiſtance is ſtill further inferred and preſt upon us, by conſidering the Example of our Saviour and thoſe Miraculous Powers for the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Church, which were given to the Apoſtles and firſt Preachers of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>As for our Saviour, though he could at any time have deſtroyed his Enemies by a word of his Mouth, or a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Finger, or by the leaſt act or intention of his Will, and though he could have called down ſo many Legions of deſtroying Angels to his aſſiſtance, yet he choſe rather to be an Example of Meekneſs and Humility, of Patience and Obedience to the Powers he lived under, than of Reſiſtance againſt them.</p>
            <p>And for the Apoſtles and their Succeſſors, it is well known that St. <hi>Peter,</hi> with the Sentence of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation denounced againſt them, ſtruck <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira</hi> dead; and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> threatned with the like or ſome ſuch uſage <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> and the <hi>inceſtuous Corinthian,</hi> and others; and it is commonly ſuppoſed by Learned Men, that this Power remained in the Church, of inflicting Death and Diſeaſes after a Miraculous way, till the Empire took Chriſtianity into its Protection, and then the Secular Sword was ſufficient to back the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106412:23"/> Cenſures; but now they never had a Power of inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the like Plagues or Calamities upon any that were not of their own Body, which was as much as to ſay, that God expected that they ſhould practiſe the Doctrine of paſſive Obedience, or Non-reſiſtance, with reſpect to their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, though they had a Power of Diſcipline among themſelves.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, God himſelf did ordain and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute an Arbitrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>overnment, when he appointed firſt <hi>Judges,</hi> and then <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that were inveſted with it; as appears from this, that there is no where any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of any Senate, or any number of Men that had a Power of limiting and controuling them, from the ſtrange Enormities of the Sons of <hi>Eli,</hi> from whence not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding no Rebellion; followed, from <hi>David</hi>'s kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the <hi>Amalekite</hi> without any Legal Proceſs, as <hi>Solomon</hi> was about to ſerve the Child that he was going to divide, and from the Deaths of <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Shimei,</hi> who were both of them put to death with no other Proceſs or Formality than the Kings Command; and laſtly, from the Anſwer of <hi>Rehoboham</hi> to the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> before the Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the two Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>The Fathers of Families, who were the firſt Kings, had an unaccountable Power of Life and Death over their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Slaves, all over the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and alſo by the Old <hi>Roman</hi> Law; and I do not ſpeak this as if I had any fancy to be a Slave, but this was moſtly the Government in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and ſo it continues to be to this Day; and God by appointing it in ſome Caſes, hath ſhewn undeniably that it is more ſutable to the Will of God, and to the Happineſs of Men, that a Government ſhould be Arbitrary, than that every Man ſhould do that which is <hi>right in his own Eyes;</hi> as it was with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> after the Death of <hi>Samſon,</hi> when the Scripture tells us there <hi>was no King in Iſrael,</hi> for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106412:24"/> a <hi>King</hi> and a <hi>Judge</hi> were in Authority the ſame, only the one was Hereditary, and the other was not.</p>
            <p>And now to apply all this to a <hi>Popiſh, Succeſſor,</hi> or on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that is <hi>reputed</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> which the diſturbers of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Peace pretend ſo much to fear; it is true, that the Laws of the Land are againſt Popery, but yet it is every whit as true, that the Laws of Nature, and the Practice of Chriſtianity in all Ages, are againſt a Rebellion; and the Laws of the Land cannot warrant us to do that which the Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture forbid; it is true likewiſe, that we live in a temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Monarchy, and that the People, though they have not the executive Power, nor any ſhare in the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet they have a right of conſenting to thoſe Laws by which they ought in Juſtice to be governed; but if the King will exceed his-bounds, a Civil War is as dangerous and deſtructive in one ſort of Government as another, and conſequently Reſiſtance is in all Governments equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with bogging your Pardon for the length of this Diſcourſe, and with deſiring you, ſince I have not time, to reflect within your ſelves upon the deteſtable blackneſs of the Crime of which the Kings Enemies and yours are Guilty, upon the Horrid Conſequences that would have attended the ſucceſs of it, and to adore that Providence that hath Delivered you from it, and pay your thanks to God by Obedience to the King, Obedience in your Thoughts, Obedience in your Actions, Obedience in your Principles, and always to be mindful of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Solomon, Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought, for a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the Voice, and that which hath Wings ſhall tell the Matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
